<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A warning to the world, being sundry strange prophecies revealed to Nicholas Smith, living at Tillington neer Petworth in Sussex, shoe-maker. As he was about thirty years since in the hous of one Vickers, living in the Stert at Abbington in Berkeshire, spoken to him by a man whom he affirmeth was his lord and saviour Jesus Christ; in the presence of the said Vickers (master of the inne) one Katherine Smith, one carpenter's wife, and a maid-servant of the house, who all both saw the vision, and heard all the words of this prophesie. 1. Concerning the restauration of the creatures. 2. Concerning the Bible, and all the bookes in the world. 3. Concerning my own life and conversation, 4. Concerning this particular nation, and the whole world besides. 5. Concerning things past, things present, and things to come. / Manifested by the spirit of God to me Nicholas Smith on Matthias day last, in obedience to whose blessed will and pleasure I am now come up to London to perform the work I am commanded, and lie at the sign of the Flying-horse in Thames-street neer Dowgate where I will (by the grace of God) be ready to attest the truth hereof with my life.</title>
            <author>Smith, Nicholas, d. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93379</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E211_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212591</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871196</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871196</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157738</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93379)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157738)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 37:E211[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A warning to the world, being sundry strange prophecies revealed to Nicholas Smith, living at Tillington neer Petworth in Sussex, shoe-maker. As he was about thirty years since in the hous of one Vickers, living in the Stert at Abbington in Berkeshire, spoken to him by a man whom he affirmeth was his lord and saviour Jesus Christ; in the presence of the said Vickers (master of the inne) one Katherine Smith, one carpenter's wife, and a maid-servant of the house, who all both saw the vision, and heard all the words of this prophesie. 1. Concerning the restauration of the creatures. 2. Concerning the Bible, and all the bookes in the world. 3. Concerning my own life and conversation, 4. Concerning this particular nation, and the whole world besides. 5. Concerning things past, things present, and things to come. / Manifested by the spirit of God to me Nicholas Smith on Matthias day last, in obedience to whose blessed will and pleasure I am now come up to London to perform the work I am commanded, and lie at the sign of the Flying-horse in Thames-street neer Dowgate where I will (by the grace of God) be ready to attest the truth hereof with my life.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Nicholas, d. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>In this edition line 6 ends "Ni-"; line 7 ends "Pet-"; line 16 ends "prophesie".</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Aprill 1st 1653"; "I think formerly".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Apparitions and miracles --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157738:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A WARNING TO THE WORLD, <hi>BEING</hi> Sundry ſtrange Propheſies Revealed to <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Smith,</hi> living at Tillington neer Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth in SUSSEX, Shoe-maker.</p>
            <p>As he was about 30 Years ſince in the Houſ of one <hi>Vickers,</hi> living in the <hi>Stert</hi> at <hi>Abbington</hi> in <hi>Berkeſhire,</hi> ſpoken to him by a Man whom he affirmeth was his Lord and Saviour JESUS CHRIST; In the preſence of the ſaid <hi>Vickers (Maſter of the Inne)</hi> one <hi>Katherine Smith,</hi> one <hi>Carpenter's</hi> wife, and a Maid-ſervant of the Houſe, who all both ſaw the <hi>Viſion,</hi> and heard all the words of this <hi>Propheſie.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Reſtauration <hi>of the CREAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Concerning the</hi> Bible, <hi>and all the Bookes in the world.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Concerning my own life and converſation,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Concerning this particular Nation, and the whole World beſides.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Concerning things paſt, things preſent, and things to come.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Manifeſted by the Spirit of God to me <hi>Nicholas Smith</hi> on <hi>Matthias</hi> day laſt, In Obedience to whoſe bleſſed Will and Pleaſure I am now come up to <hi>London</hi> to perform the Work I am commanded, and lie at the ſign of the <hi>Flying-horſe</hi> in <hi>Thames-ſtreet</hi> neer <hi>Dowgate;</hi> where I will (by the Grace of God) be ready to atteſt the truth hereof with my Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>N. Smith.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prophecies">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:157738:2"/>
            <head>Wonderfull PROPHECIES.</head>
            <p>IN the latter end of the reign of King <hi>James,</hi> at <hi>Abbington</hi> in <hi>Barkeſhire,</hi> being in one <hi>Vickers</hi> his Houſe in the <hi>Stert,</hi> I ſaw a Man that told me the things that ſhould happen unto this Kingdome; One remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able thing was, <hi>One</hi> Army <hi>ſhould lye at</hi> Abbington, <hi>and another Army</hi> at Oxford, <hi>and</hi> That theſe two ſhould fight one againſt another; but God would judge them for their Brother <hi>bloud;</hi> He told me many remarkeable things concerning my own <hi>Converſation</hi> which have already come to paſſe, and many things that are yet to come, which is admirable: many things are yet to come to paſſe concerning the whole world; He told me, <hi>That all the</hi> Books <hi>in the whole World ſhould be taken away from the uſe of man,</hi> the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was ſhewed me, <hi>ſome had Books, but they would have no body but themſelves to read in them, therefore they ſhall have none to read in; ſome ſaid they were</hi> Litter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>therefore they ſhall not have a</hi> Letter <hi>to ſee; ſome ſay,</hi> They muſt be more ſpirituall, they ſhall have five Years time to Exerciſe the Gifts of the Spirit; At that time the Creature ſhall be delivered from the vain Converſation of men that are now ſubject unto vanity; Every one muſt confeſs their ſinnes one to another; Every Woman that bares Children, muſt after that time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the true Father of them; he muſt take them home, and keep them whilſt they are young, and they muſt work for him when he is old: at that day, every one will be in perplexity, God judgeth every man according to his works, all men ſhall be judged according unto him that earneth but 10d. a day, if one earn 2s. 6d. a day, he muſt work three times ſo hard, elſe he wil be judged for a Thief; He appointed me to make Paper according to his direction, and to preſent it to him whom they that love him not, call him their King; and bid me tel him, That He ſhal cauſe the Scripture tobe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in that paper; <hi>tell him,</hi> There are great abominations committed in the Land, ſome men find fault with the pride of other men that ride in Coaches, yet pull them out, &amp; go into them themſelves in the ſight of the People, and the People find fault with it; if he wil not hear thee, carry it to thee <hi>Speaker</hi> tell him what he ſhall do to it; if he neglect it, tell the <hi>Major</hi> and the <hi>Sheriffe</hi> of it, carry it to the <hi>Exchange,</hi> and give it to the <hi>Merchants</hi> freely, if
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157738:2"/> they neglect it, it will be ill for them all; get one to go with thee to ſet men at work, make a Box, let him carry it, ſee that thou do not touch it, if there be a Stone-wall before thee, if the wall remove, thou muſt go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward; adviſe them in the Cities to carry their neceſſary Goods into the Country, God will not have ſo many to live ſo neer together, every man ſhall be reſtored to the condition as <hi>Adam</hi> was after his fall, he was aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his ſins, humbled himſelf before God; but men are fallen ſo far now, they ſin in the preſence of God, ſaying, They will confeſs their ſins to God, yet act it in his Preſence, and are proud of it; Ask them if they know God in their own boſom? ask them if they know the Image wherin they were crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? adviſe all men that they ſpoile not Barly, for they muſt learn to drink water, they ſhould do good to their enemies, they ſhould feed them, but they will not feed their Children for fear their enemies ſhould eat part of it; they had rather plant Thornes and Briers, then to plant fruit-trees; they ſhould have repaired that which Satan defaced, if they had planted fruit-trees in the fields, they might have had the leaves of them; thou ſhalt ſee a Cart-load of Skins, being Records, Propheſie againſt them, ſay they ſhall bear record no longer; Prophecy unto them on the right hand, and on the left, Tell them, they ſhould take heed, the place where they ſit ſhall burn like a furnace, they think they can eaſily get forth, but they that are without ſide ſhal keep them in <hi>Chancery;</hi> there will be new mony, at that place beat out the ſtamp which was before; and if they ask thee why thou didſt not beat out that which was before, tell them, He knows what it is to be a King: <hi>Ceſar</hi> muſt account for what he hath taken more then what is his; The Kings of the Earth make money, and buy ſuch things as they lack, and when they lack mony, they ſend for it again; Tell them how they ſhould agree with their Adverſaries that would make Peace with them Give them Peace offerings rather then take any: Impoſe upon them the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as all men may underſtand it; ſhew them how they ſhould ſubdue all their enemies under them, kil none of them, but take oppertunity to do them good; you can ſend a Man a thouſand miles, &amp; he findeth him to whom you ſend; you find not the way to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> I have ſought Counſel &amp; Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the wiſe and Learned men of this Kingdom, whom this Perſon that appeared to me may be, but they all refuſe to give me inſtruction; when all men neglected me, the Lord manifeſted himſelfe unto me, entring into me by the power of the Spirit, judging of me what I had don in the fleſh, mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſting himſelfe to be my ſalvation, whom I ſaw at <hi>Abington:</hi> the manner of the cumming of the Spirit of the Lord Jeſus upon me, was by touching lightly the haire of my head, ſo ſoaking down into my head, it made all my neck and ſhoulders to riſe; after two hours, it entred into my ſoule; whereupon I being in great fear and trouble, cryed unto my Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, beſeeching him to interceed for me unto God my Father, and I heard
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157738:3"/> a voice to my vnderſtanding, ſaying, <hi>Thou doſt not pray;</hi> my Anſwer was <hi>Lord thou knowest I do pray,</hi> he anſwered again, <hi>not with all thy heart;</hi> I entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Lord to ſearch my heart, and try it, feelingly it removed from the place where it was, to my heart, bringing my prayers to remembrance, <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king me,</hi> whether God would accept of ſuch prayers as I had prayed former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I was queſtioned of all the intents and purpoſes of my heart, what I had done, and what I intended to do, asking me, wherefore I did work? an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering him, I told him to live; he ſaid to me, <hi>That I was not willing to die to live with Chriſt;</hi> I ſaid, I waited the pleaſure of the Lord, I was adjudged for the Tranſgreſſion of the whole Law of God, and for oppoſition againſt the Government of my Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> my underſtanding was opened, and I was ſhewed what it was, and I was ſhewed his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and what it was. He told me, I ſhould be firſt up in my family, and laſt abed; I ſhould ſee all things in good Order in the morning, I ſhould cauſe all my Family to come together, cauſe a Chapter to be read, and pray with them, and for them, I ſhould earn my own bread, and fetch my own Water, I muſt give to every one rather then receive, I ſhould uſe as much as I could of the Talent which God gave me, but as little as I could of that which is committed unto Satan; Gods Talent is a reaſonable underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul, which every one ought to improve to the glory of God, the good of himſelf and others; that which is committed to Satan, is the earth and the glory thereof, I was judged for enmity againſt God my heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I acknowledged it was true, I was asked then, How I thought to ſcape the damnation of hell? I ſaid it was that <hi>wound</hi> which we received in our firſt Parents, and it coſt the precious blood of my Lord and Saviour: It was asked me, Whether I had no other hope? I anſwered, <hi>No,</hi> There was no other Name under heaven whereby I may be ſaved: And I ſaid, I knew if my Lord and Saviour was pleaſed to apply one plaiſter of his precious blood with his own hand to this my wound, which was a pain upon the midſt of my belly: immeoiately upon my Faith and confidence the paine departed from me; then I gave thanks to my Lord and Saviour: he ſaid, yet thou maiſt ſin a ſin and be damned: I entreated him tell me what it was; he ſhewed me the revelation where it is to be found: Take heed that ye are not aſhamed to behold the appearing of my Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> glory, honour, and worſhip to his holy Name for ever.</p>
            <p>Would you have me tell you what God hath done for my ſoule: I wiſh that all men did fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>I have ſought the Counſell of ſeveral Miniſters this many years; I ſpoke of it to Mr. <hi>Hilton</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Billinghurſt</hi> in <hi>Suſſex</hi> 14. years ſince, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of his neighbours: I asked ſeven Miniſters at one time, what I might do to be ſaved? they ſaid it was a neceſſary queſtion to be asked, but they ſaid it was not the buſineſſe of the day, therefore they deferred it, but ſaid it
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157738:3"/> ſhould be anſwered; the time paſt one year, I deſired to be ſatisfied of ſome inſtruction of the Scripture by ſome learned men; and deſiring them to tel me whom they thought he might be that ſpoke to me at <hi>Abbington;</hi> I invited Doct. <hi>Chanel</hi> to my houſe, and twelve Miniſters beſides to try my Faith whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was rightly grounded upon the word of God according unto his wil; and I deſired them to tell me whom they thought it might be that told me all things remarkeable that had and ſhould happen unto me; he ſaid that there was no man able to tell me ſuch things; he ſaid I was deluded: I told him how he ſhould know whether I was or not, for he bid me invite you to my houſe, but he ſaid you would not come; if you would come to morrow, then I ſhall think that I am deluded; when the morrow was come, there came never a man which I invited. My Lord and Saviour told me 28. yeares before, there would a Miniſter ſend me word that he would come to me upon a <hi>Tueſday,</hi> he ſaid I ſhould take heed, for he was the Devill; hee ſaid make thy Will, ſet thy houſe in Order, make cleane thy houſe, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thy ſelfe before God, fetch a burden of Straw, and lie naked in it all night: ſo I cauſed Doctor <hi>Chanel</hi> to make my Will, I lay in the ſtraw, a Miniſter came to perſwade me that I ſhould grant him one thing before I know what it was, that I ſhould put no more truſt in my Lord and Saviour which I ſpake with at <hi>Abbington;</hi> then I remembred four men that was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned unto me, which were Miniſters, I was appointed to go to them and command them to chooſe two a piece, whom they pleaſed, to come to my houſe and judge me, and things which I ſhould make known unto them; I was appointed to chuſe a Witneſs in the morning before they came, and tel him what they ſhould ſay when they did come, and what I was appointed to do, and ſay to them: I asked four queſtions in ſeven years; the firſt was, <hi>How I ſhould be born againe?</hi> the ſecond was, <hi>What I ſhould do to be ſaved?</hi> the third queſtion was, <hi>The bones of the Paſchal Lamb being not broken, whether it ſignifies any thing in our dayes or not?</hi> The fourth, <hi>If a man takes his Wife in the act of Adultery, whether he ought to put her away or not?</hi> But they gave me no ſatisfactory anſwer; one was angry with me, becauſe I ſaid that a man could not be born of the Water of Baptiſm, I thank the Lord that he hath ſatisfied me that all men that will enter into his governmen, muſt be born up by his Word and by his Spirit: he that will be ſaved muſt be zealous of the honour and glory of Jeſus Chriſt which was crucified at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> they that will be his body muſt keep his inſtructions; they that will be his Spouſe ſhould not joyne themſelves unto an Harlot; ye that have received the firſt fruits of the Spirit, ſigh and groan within your ſelves, waiting for the manifeſtation of the Sonnes of God, to wit, the redemption of our bodies, I mean our deliverance from the power of Tyranny, which forceth us to kill our enemies, ſometimes our friends for their will and plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:157738:4"/> our Lord hath ſhewed that we ſhould doe good unto our Enemies, and then we ſhould do good unto our friends. After the day of Reſtauration, the Horſes, the Kine, and thoſe neceſſary Creatures will be ſubject unto none but unto thoſe that are ſubject unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> and men ſhall be knowne to be Chriſtians by the gifts of God; the Creatures will be ſubject unto them, as it is ſaid, <hi>The Creature ſhall be delivered into the glorious liberty of the Sonnes of God:</hi> Men of <hi>England,</hi> ſubject your ſelves unto the Goſpel and Government of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, as it is briefly made manifeſt in the four Evangeliſts; leſt the Creature be delivered from the uſe and comfort of this Nation, know the onely true God in your own bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, know that the Spirit of the Lord is in you accuſing or excuſing: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your actions be good or evill, know Originall righteouſneſs; <hi>For this is eternall life, that ye know the onely true God in your owne boſomes, and Jeſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent.</hi> My Lord ſhewed me that it was very dangerous to dye in debt; we ſhould agree with our Adverſaries while we are in the way: if any man treſpaſſe againſt us we ſhould forgive him, and do him ſome good: My Lord ſhewed me the Angels were very rational, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon us as we look one upon another, and judge our love unto our God; As we like the Workman-ſhip of his hands, they are offended becauſe we like not the form which he hath made: We ſhew God that we would have him make Horſes without tails, and ſome without ears; our own Toes all of a length, juſt ſtrait and ſquare; ſome feet a little forked, our heads and kne s bigger; our armes as big at the hands, as they are at the ſhoulders: the wood which God giveth us to build our houſes we like it not of that colour, but make it of ſome other, ſtill ſhewing our diſlike,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord have mercy upon us, The</hi> Whore of Babylon <hi>knowes no more how to bee borne againe then</hi> Nicodemus.</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>It was revealed unto me, That all Creatures ſhould be delivered from the bondage of their corruption, according to the 8 of the</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans <hi>into the glorious Liberty of the Saints, I ſeeing no men in the Government of my Lord and Saviour, was afraid that the Creatures would be taken away utterly from the uſe of Man I fell on my knees, and did beſeech the Lord, if it might be for his glory, and the eternall good of men, that it might be another year; for I did hope that their would before that time be ſome that would be in the Government of my Lord and Saviour</hi> Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>By me NICHOLAS SMITH.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="address">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:157738:4"/>
            <p>FEllow Covenanters, ſtand faſt to the word of God; The honeſt Lawyer muſt deny the firſt Article of the Lawyers faith, or elſe they will prove tranſgreſſours of the commandements, and traytours unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Lawyers faith, is, if any one come to him, and give him a fee; It is his faithfulneſs to improve all the gifts that God hath beſtowed upon him to juſtifie him in his Cauſe, though it be evill and unjuſt; So he juſtifieth the wicked for a reward, and taketh away the righteouſneſſe of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous from him. <hi>Exod. 23. 6, 7, 8. Thou ſhalt not reſt the judgement of thy poor in his Cauſe,</hi> keep thee far from a falſe matter, and the innocent and righteous ſlay thou not, for I will not juſtifie the wicked; And thou ſhalt take no gift, for the gift blindeth the wiſe, and perverteth the words of the righteous. God hath ſent you a light in a dark lanthorn; I honour God the Father in you, and I thank you and the honourable Counſellours, for ingaging us to reform according to the word of God: But as for this preſent war, be you ſure that you are not the cauſe of it, maintaine the glory of God, take no hing from your enemies that is good: I do not deſire you to take away the Law, but I entreat you that we may have it eſtabliſhed ſo, that twelve men of the Neighbourhood may have full power to give unto every Plantiffe that which is juſtly his, doing as they would be done by, as they would anſwer it before the judgement ſeat of Chriſt, think not of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity; ſuffer not the Defendant to remove it out of the Court upon any caſe, but if the Defendant become plantiffe, let him remove it to what Court he pleaſe; maintain that which is good, for that is the way to glorifie God.</p>
            <p>I wiſh there was a law in this Common-wealth, that it might open Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and ſhut Hell; that he that did confeſſe his ſinnes might be forgiven, and he that hid them afflicted; teach your Children to pray unto you, for you are the image of God: leaſt when your back is turned, they ſay we have ſeen the image of that evill one.</p>
            <p>I wiſh that no man may be puniſhed for the firſt fault, if he acknowledge it; he that is burnt in the hand, you ſhew God that you would have him burn his ſoul.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſtion,</hi> What is thy Name? Anſwer, <hi>Adam. Queſtion,</hi> Who gave you this name? Anſ. <hi>God, in the day that he Created me. Queſt.</hi> What did God doe for thee in that day? <hi>Anſw.</hi> He made me a man capable, if that I did fall to riſe again; he gave me power by his wiſdom over the work of his hands, he impowers me to go when he bids me, and to come when he calls me: he made me ears to hear, and a heart to believe, and a tongue to confeſs to his praiſe and glory, his lawes holy, righteous, juſt and good. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Doſt thou keep the Commandements? <hi>Anſw.</hi> No. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Why doſt thou not? <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe I am ſmitten with a deadly wound of a blind mind, and a heart drawne from God by the power of Satans pollutions, whereby he makes me
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157738:5"/> to run from my God by the correction of my neceſſity, to ſeeke life by the comforts of the Creature, becauſe I am alienated by wicked works from my God, the tempter draws forth my affections by unbelief, holding my face upon the Creature, and my back upon the Lord, but God is good unto me ſtill, and ſaith, Returne ye ſons of men my ſalvation is neer unto them that feare me, he ſent the Angell of his preſence, who tooke the nature of <hi>Abraham</hi> to ſhew us the way how we ſhould returne; his exſample is that way in which our heavenly Father will accept us, he have himſelf a ranſom for his Enemies, he ſet not his affection: upon the Creature, he lived long without the uſe of them, he was ſatisfied in doing the will of God, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded not a habitation upon the earth, he was willing to offer up his ſoul and body to the glory of God our heavenly Father a ranſom for his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. <hi>Queſt.</hi> Hath God given power to man to believe this? Be not faithleſs, but believe where God hath given nothing, nothing he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: ſet not thy affections on goodly buildings, nor on a heap of money, nor on Ships at Sea, neither on a curious Coach to carry thee on the way; ſettle not thy affections upon the Proprieties of the earth, leaſt when the earth burnes thy affections be there, be of that Family that Jeſus Chriſt owns, give to all the publique weale of his people, and he ſaith thou ſhalt have treaſures in Heaven, ſettle thine affections one things above, where there is pleaſure evermore at the right hand of God; ſet not thy affections on the earth, beleeve and be baptized, ſo ſhalt thou be made manifeſt to Iſrael; reſolve to die rather then to live in the pollution of Satan, reſolve to live unto God, thou knoweſt what is good, doe it as thou loveſt eternall life which is hid in Chriſt in God.</p>
            <p>We have a hedge, but the Stakes are as withs, when the wind turnes the hedges turnes, ſo it ſhelters no man that goes by it; when the Reſtauration is for five years, the ſtake ſhal ſtand under the drapping of the Church; they ſhall not ware a black garment for ever, they ſhall ware a white garment when they ſhal appear before God, they ſhall not eat an Apple but they ſhal ſave the ſeed of it, or it were better they did: they ſhal for ever make there one parrel, they ſhall not ware a Cloak but a Mantle, none ſhall bring it to him, but lay it on the ground, becauſe he ſhall ſtoop to take it up; every one of his ſociety ſhall bring to him his web, to ſee whether the threed be to little or to big; he ſhall not have a Child in his Family, his wife ſhall be Nurſe to all his ſoiety; do you ſee that they do not pull down your Houſe leſt you die deſolate, ſet to every Pillar in Pauls a Pulpet, if it lacks ſo many, your communicants muſt be Beleevers baptiz'd.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
